An Inventory of the Stephen Green collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Stephen Green collection
1946-1988
86048
Green, Stephen, creator.
Green, Stephen, collector.
21 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize boxes, 5 microfilm reels (13.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
This collection includes reports, memoranda, dispatches, microfilm, and printed matter, relating to relations between the United States and Israel since 1948, and information regarding Israeli relations with other nations. Among these documents include materials directly related to the Israeli naval and air attack on the U.S.S. Liberty on 8 June 1967 and other military incidents with direct or indirect ties to the Israeli military and defensive forces. These materials were used as research material for the books by Stephen Green, Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel (1984) and Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East (1988).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials related to Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986. An increment of materials related to Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East was acquired in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
James M. Ennes Papers, 1961-1991, Hoover Institution Archives.
Ronald G. Kukal Papers, 1967-2000, Hoover Institution Archives.
Donald Wayne Pageler Papers, 1967-1987, Hoover Institution Archives.
U.S.S. Liberty Veterans Association Collection, 1967-1996, Hoover Institution Archives.
Biographical/Historical Note
Prior to writing his first book on American-Israeli relations, Stephen Green (born May 22, 1940) had been working a field director in Somalia for Oxfam Inc., an international famine relief organization. In his own words, his work there as a relief coordinator led him to decide to write about the United States' and Israel's relationship. His first book on the topic, Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel was published in 1984 and the second book, Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East was published in 1988. Alongside these works, Green has also written other articles regarding the complex relations between the United States and Israel. As a freelance journalist, he continues to write and speak on affairs and policies regarding Israel and the Middle East.
Information obtained primarily from Contemporary Authors Online, Gale, 2010. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Gale, 2010. http://galenet.galegroup.com/servlet/BioRC
Scope and Content of Collection
The Stephen Green Collection includes reports, memoranda, dispatches, microfilm, and printed matter relating to relations between the United States and Israel since 1948, American military assistance to Israel, and information regarding Israeli relations with other nations. Among these documents include materials directly related to the Israeli naval and air attack on the U.S.S. Liberty on 8 June 1967 and other military incidents with direct or indirect ties to the Israeli military and defensive forces. These materials were used as research material for the books by Stephen Green, Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel (1984) and Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East (1988). The collection also many photocopies of U.S. Government documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act and related correspondence. The collection also includes drafts of chapters from Living by the Sword and some correspondence of Stephen Green relating to accumulation of the research material.
For all of the documents with multiple dates present, such as date of origination, date of declassification and/or sanitation, the date of the origination of the document is used. The original order of the materials as they were when initially acquired was retained as much as possible. The arrangement for the papers is as follows: Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel Research Documents, Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East Research Documents and Oversize File.
The series Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel Research Documents(Boxes 1-9 and Oversize Boxes 23 and 24) includes research materials used for the book Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel. These research materials include reports, memoranda, dispatches, and printed matter relating to relations between the United States and Israel since 1948. Many of these materials specifically relate to the Israeli naval and air attacks, such as the Israeli attack on the U.S.S. Liberty on 8 June 1967. The series also includes some correspondence related to accumulation of the research material and photocopies of U.S. Government documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act.
A significant percentage of the research materials collected for this series came from the following institutions: The Lyndon Baines Johnson Presidential Library ( http://www.lbjlibrary.org/collections/), the Dwight D. Eisenhower library ( http://www.eisenhower.archives.gov/), and the National Archives of Records Administration ( http://www.archives.gov/research/). This series also includes 5 reels of microfilm of research materials.
The series Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East Research Documents (Boxes 10-22 and Oversize Boxes 23-25) includes research materials used for Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East. These materials include reports, memoranda, dispatches, and printed matter relating to the complex relations between the United States and Israel from 1948 to the publication of the book in 1988 and correspondence related to accumulation of the research. The series also includes photocopies of U.S. Government documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act and document.
The series Oversize File (Boxes 23-25) contains research materials from both Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel and Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East. The bulk of the series includes duplication of newspaper articles, majority coming from The New York Times and The Washington Post. This series is arranged first by specific book and physical placement is arranged by size.
Citations:
Green, Stephen. Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel, New York, William Morrow and Company, Inc., 1984
Green Stephen. Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East, Brattleboro, VT, Amana Books, 1988
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Liberty (Ship); United States. Navy.; Israel-Arab War, 1967--Naval operations.; Jewish-Arab relations.; Military assistance, American--Israel.; United States--Foreign relations--Israel.; Israel--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Armed Forces--Mediterranean Sea.
Collection Contents
- Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel Research Documents, 1946-1983 (Box 1-9)
  This series includes documents used as research materials specifically for this book. These materials consist of reports, memoranda, dispatches, printed matter, microfilm, and some correspondence related to accumulation of the research material. The series also includes photocopies of U.S. Government documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act. The bulk of the series is arranged according to specific chapter or range of chapters. The arrangement for the subseries of collected items is by subject. Materials related to this series can also be found in the Oversize File series.
  - Chapter 2, 1947-1949, 1954, 1964-1967, 1982, undated (Folder 1: 1)
    Documents not used
  - Chapter 2, 1948-1949, 1971 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Chapter 2, 1948, 1954, 1964-1967 (Folder 1: 3)
    Documents not used. Includes correspondence between collector and John R. Burke from the Classification/Declassification Center, U.S. Department of State. See also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 1.
  - Chapter 2, 1947-1948 (Folder 1: 4)
    Documents not used.
  - Chapters 2 and 3, 1948-1950, 1974 (Folder 1: 5-6)
    Documents referred to for research purposes. These documents may not have been footnoted in the final version of the book
  - Chapters 2 and 3, 1948 January-October (Folder 1: 7)
    Contains documents which may or may not have been used in the final versions of Chapters 2 and 3. Includes correspondence between collector and John R. Burke from the Classification/Declassification Center, U.S. Department of State
  - Chapters 2 and 3, 1948, 1954, 1956-1957, 1967, 1975, 1983 (Folder 1: 8)
    Unsorted documents, contains documents which may or may not have been used in the final versions of Chapters 2 and 3.
  - Chapters 2 and 3, 1948-1950 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Chapters 2 and 3, 1948-1949, 1954, 1965-1967, 1976 (Folder 2: 1-2)
    Unsorted documents, contains documents which may or may not have been used in the final versions of Chapters 2 and 3. See Also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 1.
  - Chapter 3, 1946, 1948-1949 (Folder 2: 3)
    Documents used
  - Chapter 3, 1948-1949 (Folder 2: 4)
    Documents not used pertaining to section Arms Traffic
  - Chapter 3, 1948-1949, 1951, 1953 (Folder 2: 5)
    Documents not used pertaining to section Diplomacy in a War Zone
  - Chapter 3, 1949 (Folder 2: 6)
    Documents not used pertaining to section Military Attache
  - Chapter 3, 1946-1949 (Folder 2: 7)
    Documents not used pertaining to section A Strategic View
  - Chapter 3, 1946-1951, 1953, 1962 (Folder 2: 8-10)
  - Chapter 3, 1946-1956, 1974 (Folder 3: 1-3)
  - Chapter 3, 1947-1949 (Folder 3: 4-7)
    Unsorted documents
  - Chapter 4, 1953-1954, 1968 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Chapter 5, 1953-1956, 1972, 1976, 1980 (Folder 3: 9-10)
    Documents used and other notes. Includes primary and secondary source research. See Also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 2.
  - Chapter 5, 1977-1978 (Folder 4:1)
  - Chapter 5, 1954 (Folder 4:2)
  - Chapter 5, 1953-1954, 1982 (Folder 4:3)
    documents not used. Also includes correspondence generating from the Department of the Air Force regarding releasing information to Stephen Green, 1982 April 13
  - Chapter 5, 1955-1958, 1960, 1977 (Folder 4:4)
    Documents not used and other notes. See Also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 3.
  - Chapter 6, 1954-1956 (Folder 4:5)
    Documents footnoted. See Also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 4.
  - Chapter 6, 1951, 1954-1959, 1964 (Folder 4:6-10)
    Includes unsorted documents, contains documents and notes which may or may not have been used for the final version of Chapter 6
  - Chapter 6, 1953, 1956-1960, 1964 (Folder 5:1-3)
    Unsorted documents, contains documents and notes which may or may not have been used for the final version of Chapter 6. See Also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 5.
  - Chapter 7, 1954-1968, 1971, 1974-1982 (Folder 5:4-6)
    Documents footnoted. Also includes notes used and correspondence. See Also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 6.
  - Chapter 7, 1961, 1966, 1970, 1973-1978 (Folder 5:7-8)
    Documents not used. See Also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 2.
  - Chapter 7, 1953-1958, 1966, 1968, 1974, 1978-1982 (Folder 6:1-2)
  - Chapter 7, 1953-1956, 1966-1968, 1974-1978, 1982 (Folder 6:3)
    Documents not used. Also includes correspondence between Stephen Green and John Leavitt 1982 November 10
  - Chapter 7, 1966 December 14 (Folder 6:4)
    Document not used
  - Chapter 8, 1963, 1965-1967, undated (Folder 6:5)
    Documents footnoted, also includes correspondence
  - Chapter 8, 1963, 1967-1968 (Folder 6:6)
    Documents footnoted
  - Chapters 8 and 10, 1965-1968 (Folder 6:7-8)
  - Chapters 8 and 10, 1964-1967, 1976 (Folder 7:1)
  - Chapter 9, 1967, 1981 (Folder 7:2)
    Notes and unsorted documents. See also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 7
  - Chapter 9, 1967-1969, 1981-1983 (Folder 7:3)
    Notes and unsorted documents. Also includes correspondence related to Stephen Green?s requests to the Department of Defense made under the Freedom of Information Act, 1981-1982 and correspondence with James M. Ennes, 1983 May - July
  - Chapter 9, 1967, 1982-1983 (Folder 7:4)
    Notes and unsorted documents. Also includes correspondence with James M. Ennes, 1982 December ? 1983 February. Also includes the report The Attack on the Liberty Incident created by the Israeli Defense Forces History Department Research and Instruction Branch, 1981 June
  - Chapter 9, 1967, 1969, 1982 (Folder 7:5)
    Notes and unsorted documents.Also includes correspondence with James M. Ennes and Stan E. White, 1982 April-June. Also includes correspondence with pertaining to a request to the Department of Defense under the Freedom of Information Act, 1982
  - Chapter 9, 1967-1968, 1980, 1982 (Folder 7:6)
  - Chapter 9, 1958-1960, 1967, 1980-1981, 1983 (Folder 7:7)
    Documents not used. Also includes materials related correspondence, 1981 and 1983 and materials obtained from James M. Ennes
  - Chapter 9, 1967, 1962, undated (Folder 7:8)
    Documents not used. Also includes correspondence between Stephen Green and the Department of the Navy regarding his requests for documents under the Freedom of Information Act, 1982 November 24
  - Chapter 9, 1966-1968, 1982-1983 (Folder 8:1-3)
    Documents not used. See also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 8.
  - Chapter 9, 1967-1968, 1980, 1982 (Folder 8:4)
    Documents not used. Also includes correspondence between James M. Ennes and the Department of State pertaining to his request for documents under the Freedom of Information Act, 1980 and other correspondence, 1982
  - Chapter 10, 1980, 1983 (Folder 8:5)
    Documents used. See also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 4
  - Subject File, 1965-1983 (Folder 8-9:)
    - Central Intelligence Agency, 1977, 1983, undated (Folder 8:6)
      Includes documents, correspondence, and other collected materials
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation (Folder 9:1-3)
      Memoranda and telegrams
    - Israeli Terrorism Project and Sheersburg, 1979, circa 1980-1981 (Folder 9:4)
    - Report on the Israeli attack on the U.S.S. Liberty, 1975 (Folder 9:5)
    - U.S. Department of State, 1967-1969, 1981-1982, undated (Folder 9:6-8)
    - U.S. Department of State, 1975 October (Folder 9:9)
      Includes materials pertaining to the Eliat Attack, October 1967
    - Miscellany, 1965-1967, 1969, 1981 (Folder 9:10)
  - 5 microfilm reels with research materials used in chapters 3 and 8 (Folder Microfilm Shelf)
- Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East Research Documents, 1946-1988 (Box 10-22)
  This series includes documents used as research materials specifically for this book. These materials include reports, memoranda, dispatches, and printed matter relating to the complex relations between the United States and Israel from 1948 to the publication of the book in 1988. This series also includes correspondence related to accumulation of the research. Also included are photocopies of U.S. Government documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act and related correspondence. This series has been arranged into three subseries: Chapter Drafts, Documents Used and Notes, and General Research Materials. Chapter Drafts and Documents Used and Notes have been arranged by specific chapter or range of chapters. General Research Materials have been arranged according the original order as acquired when the donation of the collection was made. Materials related to this series can also be found in the Oversize File series.
  - Chapter drafts, undated (Folder 10-11:)
    - Chapter 1, undated (Folder 10:1)
    - Chapter 2, undated (Folder 10:2)
    - Chapter 3, undated (Folder 10:3)
    - Chapter 4, undated (Folder 10:4)
    - Chapter 5, undated (Folder 10:5)
      Includes final draft
    - Chapter 6, undated (Folder 10:6)
    - Chapter 7, undated (Folder 10:7)
    - Chapter 8, undated (Folder 10:8)
    - Chapter 9, undated (Folder 10:9)
      some drafts say "Chapter 10" but the final result is Chapter 9 of the book
    - Chapter 10, undated (Folder 10:10)
      see also Oversize File Box 25 Folder 2 for an additional draft
    - Chapter 11, undated (Folder 11:1)
      see also Oversize File Box 25 Folder 3 for an additional draft
    - Chapter 12, undated (Folder 11:2)
    - Chapter 13, undated (Folder 11:3)
      see also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 6 for an additional draft
  - Documents used and notes, 1941-1988 (Folder 11-21:)
    Arranged by chapter
    - Chapter 1, 1941, 1947-1948, 1953-1957, 1964-1969, 1979-1985, undated (Folder 11:4-10)
      Includes reports, notes, memoranda, related correspondence, press clippings, and other printed materials
    - Chapter 1, 1948, 1953, 1957, 1965-1968, 1983-1984, undated (Folder 12:1-3)
      Also includes related correspondence
    - Chapter 2, 1967-1969, 1974, 1982-1985 (Folder 12:4-6)
      See also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 9
    - Chapters 2, 3 and 4, 1967-1968, 1983-1984 (Folder 12:7)
    - Chapter 3, 1969-1972, 1982, 1984, 1987, undated (Folder 12:8-10)
      Includes related correspondence and documents pertaining to Freedom of Information Act requests by Stephen Green and related litigation. See also Oversize File Box 23 Folder 10
    - Chapter 4, 1967-1969, 1974, 1978-1979, 1981, undated (Folder 13:1-5)
      See also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 5
    - Chapters 4 and 5, 1967, 1978, 1983 (Folder 13:6)
    - Chapter 5, 1972-1973, 1979, 1984-1985 (Folder 13:7-9)
      Includes related correspondence and documents pertaining to Freedom of Information Act requests by Stephen Green and related litigation
    - Chapter 6, 1975, 1981, 1984-1986, undated (Folder 13:10-11)
      Includes related correspondence and documents pertaining to Freedom of Information Act requests by Stephen Green and related litigation, see also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 6 and Oversize File Box 24 Folder 11.
    - Chapter 6, 1980 (Folder 14:1)
    - Chapters 6 and 7, 1968-1986, circa 1970s, undated (Folder 14:2-9)
    - Chapters 6 and 7, 1972-1973, 1984 (Folder 15:1)
      See also Oversize Box 25 Folder 1
    - Chapter 7, 1978-1980 (Folder 15:2)
    - Chapter 8, 1987 March 3, undated (Folder 15:3)
      Includes interview notes and correspondence
    - Chapter 8, 1982 March 30 (Folder 15:4)
      Enforcement of the United States Arms Embargo Against South Africa
    - Chapter 8, 1949, 1974, 1976-1980, 1984-1986 (Folder 15:5-9)
      Israeli-South African relations and the Vela Incident
    - Chapter 8, 1976-1986 (Folder 16:1-2)
    - Chapter 8, 1981, undated (Folder 16:3)
      Names and numbers
    - Chapter 8, 1984 (Folder 16:4)
      Nuclear arms verification information
    - Chapter 8, 1975, 1977, 1979, 1985, 1987 (Folder 16:5)
      Other documents used and notes including information pertaining to U.S. foreign policy and the National Security Council
    - Chapter 8, 1975-1976, 1978-1979 (Folder 16:6)
    - Chapters 8, 9, and 10, 1974, 1982-1983, 1985 (Folder 16:7-9)
      Includes materials related to a request made under the Freedom of Information Act and associated litigation
    - Chapters 8, 9, and 10, circa 1970s, 1973-1977, 1979, 1981, 1983, 1985 (Folder 17:1-2)
    - Chapter 9, circa 1980s, 1983, 1987 (Folder 17:3)
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1981, 1986 (Folder 17:4)
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1978, 1981, 1983-1984, 1987, undated (Folder 17:5-7)
      See also Oversize File Box 24 Folder 13 and Box 25 Folder 3.
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1977-1979, 1986-1987 (Folder 18:1)
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1981 (Folder 18:2)
      Includes documents and notes pertaining to Beirut, Lebanon
    - Chapter 11, 1982-1985, undated (Folder 18:3-9)
    - Chapters 11, 12, and 13, 1952, 1971, 1974, 1978, 1980-1987 (Folder 19:1-5)
    - Chapter 12 and 13, 1980-1981, 1984, 1986-1987 (Folder 19:6-7)
    - Chapter 12 and 13, 1949, 1977, 1979, 1981-1987, undated (Folder 20:1-7)
    - Chapter 13, 1987 May 26-28 (Folder 21:1-2)
      R&D Cooperation Conference
  - Egypt Notes, undated (Folder 21:3)
  - General Research Materials and Miscellaneous Notes, 1985 August 20 (Folder 21:4)
    Includes document A Judicial Examination of the Israeli Attack on the 'USS Liberty'
  - General Research Materials and Miscellaneous Notes, 1973-1975, 1981, undated (Folder 21:5-9)
  - General Research Materials and Miscellaneous Notes, 1973-1977, 1979, 1981-1987, undated (Folder 22:1-6)
    see also Oversize File Box 25 Folders 7, 8, and 9
- Oversize File, 1948-1983 (Box 23-25)
  Includes oversize materials from Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel and Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East. The bulk of the series includes duplication of newspaper articles, the majority coming from The New York Times and The Washington Post. This series is arranged first by specific book and physical placement is arranged by size.
  - Taking Sides: America's Secret Relations with a Militant Israel Collection, 1948-1963 (Folder 23-24:)
    Includes news articles and other documents used in the research process for Taking Sides.
    - Chapter 2, 1948, 1961, 1967 (Folder 23:1)
    - Chapters 2 and 3, 1956, 1965, undated (Folder 24:1)
      Documents referred to
    - Chapter 5, 1948, 1953-1954, 1961, 1965 (Folder 23:2)
    - Chapter 5, 1952, 1962, 1964 (Folder 23:3)
    - Chapter 6, 1956, circa 1967 (Folder 23:4)
    - Chapter 6, 1948, undated (Folder 23:5)
      Unsorted documents, contains documents and notes which may or may not have been used for the final version of Chapter 6
    - Chapter 7, 1954, 1956, 1960-1962, 1965, 1971, 1974 (Folder 23:6)
    - Chapter 7, 1960-1963, 1969-1970, 1972-1973, 1975-1976, 1978, circa 1980 (Folder 24:2)
    - Chapter 8, 1963-1964 (Folder 24:3)
    - Chapter 9, 1967 (Folder 23:7)
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1961-1962, 1966-1967 (Folder 23:8)
    - Chapter 10, 1953-1954, 1967, 1978, 1982 (Folder 24:4)
  - Living by the Sword: America and Israel in the Middle East Collection, 1946-1983 (Folder 23-25:)
    Includes news articles and other documents used in the research process for Living by the Sword. Also includes handwritten drafts for chapters 10, 11 and 13.
    - Chapter 2, 1968 (Folder 23:9)
    - Chapter 3, 1968-1969 (Folder 23:10)
      Documents used, East Ghor articles
    - Chapter 4, 1967-1970, 1983 (Folder 24:5)
    - Chapter 6, 1973, 1976-1977 (Folder 24:6)
    - Chapter 6, 1973, 1979 (Folder 24:11)
    - Chapters 6 and 7, 1973 (Folder 25:1)
    - Chapter 8, 1979-1980 (Folder 24:12)
    - Chapters 9 and 10, 1981 (Folder 24:13)
    - Chapter 10, undated (Folder 25:2)
      Draft
    - Chapter 10, 1981 (Folder 25:3)
    - Chapter 11, undated (Folder 25:4)
    - Chapter 11, 1982-1983 (Folder 25:5)
    - Chapter 13, undated (Folder 25:6)
    - General Research Materials, 1973, undated (Folder 23:14)
    - General Research Materials, 1973, 1975-1976, 1981, 1983, 1986-1987 (Folder 25:7-9)